New York State Executive Advisory Committee on the Administration of Justice; Records apap091
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
New York State Executive Advisory Commission on the Administration of Justice Records
1981-1983
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
New York (State). Executive Advisory Commission on the Administration of Justice
apap091
0.66 cubic ft.
The New York State Executive Advisory Commission on the Administration of Justice Records is composed of materials retained by Vincent O'Leary, a past president of the State University of New York at Albany and member of the commission. The collection provides insight into the inner workings and public exchanges of the commission members as they discussed and dealt with problems associated with the criminal justice system.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by the Office of the President on behalf of Vincent O'Leary in June 1983.
Organizational Sketch
The New York State Executive Advisory Commission was established on March 19, 1981 by Governor Hugh Carey. The commission was made up of primarily private citizens, including lawyers, businessmen, and teachers. The chair of the commission was Arthur Liman. Members of the commission included: Arthur Barnes, President of the New York Urban Coalition; Richard L. Gelb, Bristol-Myers Company; Betsy Gotbaum, New York City Police Foundation; Simon P. Gourdine, Esq., National Basketball Association; Ralph Graves, Editorial Director; Thomas F. Hastings, Executive Director of Rochester Jobs, Inc.; Mrs. Ruth Hinerfeld, League of Women Voters; Alan Hruska, Esq., Cravath, Swain and Moore; Patricia M. Hynes, Esq., Executive Assistant U.S. Attorney; Salvatore R. Martoche, Esq.; Robert B. McKay, Esq., Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies; Robert M. Morgenthau, Esq., District Attorney of New York County; Archibald R. Murray, Esq., The Legal Aid Society; Vincent O'Leary, President of the State University of New York at Albany; The Honorable John F. O'Mara, Juan Ortiz, Esq.; Personnel Director for the City of New York; The Honorable Harold R. Tyler, Jr.; H. Richard Uviller, Esq., Professor of Law; Mrs. Martha Redfield Wallace; The Henry Luce Foundation, and Steven E. Landers, Esq., Secretary to the Commission.
The mission of the commission was to evaluate current problems with the criminal justice system, such as prison overcrowding, prison sentencing, parole law and practices, as well as jury selection reform. The commission's goal was also to brainstorm new and innovative approaches to fixing those problems and establish effective criminal justice strategies that would produce "real results". The commission held meetings and hearings to gather information about and discuss those issues. The commission was disbanded in 1983.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains information about the commission, such as hearings and minutes of meetings. Information about the criminal justice system, prison overcrowding, and news clippings are also included. The collection is composed of records retained by Vincent O'Leary, who was president of the State University of New York at Albany at the time and a member of the commission.
Related collections available in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives can be found at the subject page for Criminal Justice and Prisons. The New York State Archives holds administrative and hearing files and research, hearing, and study files for the commission.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Correspondence, 1981-1983
Series 2 - Hearings, 1981-1982
Series 3 - Reports, 1981-1982
All series are arranged alphabetically.
Public Servants; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Criminal justice, Administration of--New York (State); Jury selection--New York (State); Probation--New York (State); Prison sentences--New York (State); New York (State)--Criminal Justice; Correspondence; Minutes; Reports; Clippings; New York (State)--Executive Advisory Commission on the Administration of Justice; Hughes, Carey L.; O'Leary, Vincent; Liman, Arthur L.
- Correspondence, 1981-1983; 1; 0.13 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  The Correspondence series details personal correspondence between Vincent O'Leary and other members of the commission, strategies the group took to suggest changes in the criminal justice system, and meetings about the commission itself, prison overcrowding, and the prison system. This series also references judicial reform, the federal-state relationship, and criminal justice information management.
  - Correspondence and Minutes, 1981-1982 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 1)
  - O'Leary, Vincent, Personal Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 2)
  - Prison System, 1981 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 3)
  - Prison System, 1981-1982 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 4)
  - Reports on Commission, 1981 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence), Folder 5)
- Hearings, 1981-1982; 2; 0.20 cubic ft.
  The Hearings series contains transcripts of public hearings and testimony before the commission on probation services, prison sentencing guidelines, and prison overcrowding; a court document on the transfer of inmates to the House of Detention for Men on Riker's Island; and a list of potential witnesses for a hearing on prison overcrowding. There is also a public hearing response to commission proposals and recommendations, a statement by Marie Runyon about the Harlem Restoration Project, which offered assistance in correcting the problems of unemployment and sub-standard housing in Harlem, and testimony by Barbara Van Buren about Project Green Hope, which provided supportive services to women returning to New York City from prison or referred to Project Green Hope by the courts as an alternative to incarceration.
  - Commission Hearings, 1982 (Box 1 (2-Hearings), Folder 6)
  - Court Documents, 1981-1982 (Box 1 (2-Hearings), Folder 7)
  - Prison Overcrowding, 1982 (Box 1 (2-Hearings), Folder 8)
  - Prison Overcrowding, 1982 (Box 1 (2-Hearings), Folder 9)
- Reports, 1981-1982; 3; 0.33 cubic ft.
  The Reports series contains a criminal justice information management agenda, commission proposals about changes to the criminal justice system, a draft of a bill of rights for crime victims, an agenda for the courts subcommittee, a project for law enforcement priorities and strategies for local police, news clippings about the criminal justice system, a correctional services master plan, reports on prison overcrowding and the prison system, and reports on a $500 million prison bond and the correctional system.
  - Criminal Justice Management, 1981 (Box 2 (3-Reports), Folder 1)
  - Criminal Justice System, News Clippings, 1982 (Box 2 (3-Reports), Folder 2)
  - Justice System, 1980-1982 (Box 2 (3-Reports), Folder 3)
  - Prison Overcrowding, 1981-1982 (Box 2 (3-Reports), Folder 4)
  - Prison Overcrowding, 1981-1982 (Box 2 (3-Reports), Folder 5)
  - Prison Overcrowding Report, 1982 (Box 2 (3-Reports), Folder 6)
  - Prison System, 1981-1982 (Box 2 (3-Reports), Folder 7)
  - Prison System, Reports, 1982 (Box 2 (3-Reports), Folder 8)